成為宇宙公民的夢想
The dream of becoming a citizen of the cosmos
在2000年前 誕生於此
was born here, more than two millennia ago,
亞歷山大城
in the city of Alexandria,
這座城市的名字是為了紀念它的征服者
named after and conceived by its dead conqueror,
已去世的亞歷山大大帝
Alexander the Great.
希臘的托勒密王朝
The Ptolemys, the Greek kings
繼承了亞歷山大帝國的埃及地區
who inherited the Egyptian portion of Alexander's empire,
並修建了這座圖書館
built this library
成立了相關的研究機構
and its associated research institution.
可以說 這是非常罕見的舉措
Rarely, if ever,
不僅空前 而且絕後
before or since,
從沒有一個政府會花那麼多錢
has there been a government that was willing to spend
把國家收入的大部分
so much of its gross national product
投入到對知識的獲取中
on the acquisition of knowledge.
有付出就有回報
And it paid off.
知識的大時代來臨了
Big time.
每一艘進入亞歷山大港的船隻
Every ship entering Alexandria's harbor
都要進行搜查 查的不是違禁品
was searched-- not for contraband,
而是那些放在船上的書籍手抄本
but for books that might be copied and stored here,
發現後就歸入這座當時世界上最偉大的圖書館
in what was then the greatest library on Earth.
正是在這裏 圖書館的館長埃拉托斯特尼
Here, Eratosthenes, one of the chief librarians,
準確的計算出了地球的直徑
accurately calculated the size of the Earth
並創建了地理學
and invented geography.
畢達哥拉斯
Pythagoras.
希帕蒂婭
Hypatia.
歐幾里得
Euclid.
歐幾里得在著作中闡述了幾何學的定律
Euclid set forth the precepts of geometry
2300年後 他的著作依然被世人使用
in a textbook that remained in use for 2,300 years.
《聖經•舊約》也是從這裏開始散播到人世
The Old Testament Bible comes down to us
經書的大部分在這裏被翻譯成了希臘語
mainly from the Greek translations made here.
很多偉大作品的原始手稿也保存在這裏
The original manuscripts of the masterpieces
包括希臘的喜劇 戲劇 詩歌
of Greek comedy and drama, poetry,
科學著作 工程著作
science, engineering,
醫學著作 歷史著作
medicine and history--
失落的古代文明作品被重新喚醒
the total work product
妥妥的保存在這裏
of the awakening of ancient civilization-- were kept here.
據推測 這裏的藏書
Estimates vary on the total number of scrolls.
大概有50萬卷以上
They range from 500,000
甚至多達上百萬卷
to nearly a million.
所有的這些作品
And all of it...
所有的這些書籍
all of this
現在只需要很小的一個空間
is but a tiny fraction of the information
就像你的指尖那麼大的地方就可以保存了
that you have at your fingertips at this very moment.
人類集體的知識
The collective knowledge of our species,
存在我們自己的亞歷山大電子圖書館裏
our own electronic Library of Alexandria,
只要你身上帶有相應的設備 就隨時可以獲取
may be accessed by anyone who has a device
你愛看什麼就看什麼 什麼時候想看就什麼時候看
and the interest and the freedom to do so.
可在過去的亞歷山大城 這樣的事情是不會發生的
This was not true in Alexandria,
知識只屬於某些精英人士
where knowledge belonged to the elite.
因此在公元前四世紀
So in the fourth century AD,
當暴民摧毀圖書館時
when the mob came to destroy the library
當古典文明的精華被摧毀時
and the genius of classical civilization,
沒有什麼人站起來保衛它們
there were not enough people to defend it.
等下一次的暴亂來臨時 又會發生些什麼
What will happen the next time the mob comes?
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第十三集
我們已經一起經歷了一段漫長的旅程
We've come a long way together,
我們深入了原子的內核
traveling from deep inside the heart of an atom
抵達了宇宙的邊緣
clear out to the cosmic horizon,
從時間的起源走到遙遠的未來
and from the beginning of time to the distant future.
我們是時候做一些實驗了
I think we're ready to perform an experiment.
這不是那種在實驗室裏才能做的實驗
It's not the kind of experiment that requires a laboratory.
你可以在自己的腦海裏完成它
You can do it in your head.
它稱之為"思想實驗"
It's called a "thought experiment."
選一顆星星
Pick a star--
就在我們的銀河系裏選上
any one of the hundreds of billions of stars
這數以百億顆星星中的一顆
in our Milky Way Galaxy,
其實銀河系也只不過是
which is just one galaxy
目前已知宇宙的上百億個星系中的一個
out of the hundred billion in the known universe.
這顆怎麼樣
How about that star?
或者是那一顆
Or that one?
好 就是這顆吧
Okay, this one.
有幾十個行星和衛星圍繞著它旋轉
It's orbited by dozens of planets and moons.
假設 其中的一顆
Suppose, on one of them,
上面有智能生物存在
there lives an intelligent species,
他們是這個行星裏上千萬種生命形式的一種
one the ten million life-forms on that planet,
在這些智能生物中
and there's a subgroup of that species
有一小部分生物認為他們已經發現了
who believe they have it all figured out--
這個世界就是宇宙的中心
their world is the center of the universe,
這個宇宙為他們而造
a universe made for them,
他們已經無所不知
and that they know everything they need to know about it--
擁有了圓滿的智慧
their knowledge is complete.
你覺得他們的話可以當真嗎
How seriously would you take their claim?
我們的祖先就認為
Our ancestors believed
宇宙是為他們而造的
the universe was made for them.
把人假定為世界的中心是很自然的事情
It was natural to assume that we were at the center.
畢竟 太陽和其他的星星
After all, it looks like the Sun and stars
看起來都圍繞著人類轉
all revolve around us.
我們現在還在說 太陽是"升"起來的
We still speak of the Sun "rising."
人類的語言 神話和夢想的體系結構
The architecture of our language, myths and dreams
是來自科學誕生前的時代
comes from that pre-scientific age.
在哥倫布出航發現新大陸前
This is our planet as it was known then,
人們都認為已經很瞭解這個星球了
just before Columbus set sail.
這是世界上第一個地球儀
This first globe of the Earth was cutting-edge
馬丁•貝海姆在1492年製造了這個當時是最前沿的產品
when Martin Behaim made it in 1492.
和當時的其他人一樣 他認為
Like everyone else, he believed
這幅世界地理的拼圖已經完整無缺了
that the jigsaw puzzle of geography was complete.
上面有三個大陸
There were three continents...
歐洲 非洲和亞洲
Europe, Africa and Asia,
三個大洲之間只有浩瀚的大洋
and only the great world ocean in between.
貝海姆地球儀上看不到北美洲與南美洲的存在
Behaim had no clue that North and South America even existed.
人很容易自以為是 對不對
It's easy to feel smug, right?
事實上 馬丁•貝海姆對他的世界的瞭解
Well, the fact is Martin Behaim knew infinitely more
對地球的瞭解
about his world, the Earth,
遠遠勝過我們對於宇宙的瞭解
than we know about ours, the universe.
近代有一個關于謙虛的故事
A recent lesson in humility
可以很好的作為明證
will serve to illustrate.
1912年 維克托•赫斯進行了好幾次飛行
In 1912, Victor Hess made a series of voyages
他飛越了奧地利上空
into the sky above Austria,
發現了科學家們期待已久的東西…
and found the thing that scientists love best...
一個神秘而無法理解的事件
a mystery that defied understanding
用傳統的科學無法解釋
in terms of conventional scientific wisdom.
時至今日
And even today,
100年過去了 我們仍在苦苦搜尋
a century later, we are still searching
要為赫斯的發現找一個完整的答案
for a complete explanation of what Hess found.
當時有一種新的能量剛被發現
A new kind of energy had recently been discovered,
輻射能
radioactivity.
也就是放射能
自然界中某種特定的元素會釋放出輻射
It was given off
比如鐳
by certain elements, like radium.
但空氣中也有輻射
But it was also found in the air,
在遠離放射性岩石的地方也有輻射
even far away from radioactive rocks.
它可說是無處不在
It was everywhere.
這些奇怪的能量是從哪裏來的
Where did this strange energy come from?
無人知曉
No one knew.
赫斯推測它可能來自地球上空
Hess suspected that it might come from above the Earth.
為了驗證這個假設 他攜帶著輻射探測器
To test his hypothesis, he carried radiation detectors
飛向高空
high into the sky.
他冒著乘坐氫氣球的風險
During a risky ascent in a hydrogen balloon,
他到達了海拔超過3英里的高度
he attained an altitude of more than three miles.
當他來到空氣稀薄 溫度寒冷的
When he reached the thin, cold,
大氣層中部以上時
upper half of the atmosphere...
他發現這裏的輻射值
he found that the radiation
比地面的要強2倍以上
was more than twice as strong as on the ground.
這些輻射一定是來自於更高處
The radiation must be coming from above.
因此它在地面才會比較弱
That's why its intensity was weaker on the ground--
因為地球的大氣層吸收了大部分能量
the Earth's atmosphere was absorbing most of it.
有人認為這些輻射可能來自於太陽
Some thought that the radiation might come from the Sun.
為了測試這個說法
To test that idea, Hess timed one of his ascents
赫斯在一次日食時升上高空
to coincide with a solar eclipse.
他發現日食對輻射沒有任何影響
But the eclipse had no effect on the radiation.
赫斯還發現
Hess also found that the radiation
輻射在白天和晚上的強度是一樣的
was just as strong at night as in daylight.
這些輻射是來自於高空 但不是太陽
It was coming from above, but not from the Sun.
赫斯不知道
What Hess did not know
太陽風根本就沒有那麼快的速度
was that the solar wind doesn't move that quickly.
因此 他憑著這個錯誤的理由
And so, for the wrong reason,
做出了正確的結論
he came to the right conclusion.
赫斯發現了宇宙射線
Hess had discovered cosmic rays--
那些如陣雨一般在宇宙中交錯飛灑的亞原子粒子
showers of subatomic particles that crisscross the universe
它們以光速行進著
at literally the speed of light.
如果沒有地球大氣層的保護
Without the shielding effect of the Earth's atmosphere,
它們可致人死地
they would be lethal.
某些宇宙射線攜帶的能量
Some cosmic rays can carry as much energy
與步槍中發射的子彈一樣強
as a bullet fired from a rifle.
人類花了幾十年的時間追蹤宇宙射線
It would take decades to trace those cosmic rays
才發現它們那無法想像的恐怖死亡之面
back to a death of unimaginable violence.
赫斯在奧地利上空發現的宇宙射線
The cosmic rays that Victor Hess detected
向科學家們提出了一個謎
in the skies above Austria posed a mystery to scientists.
地球上的放射性礦物質
Radioactivity in minerals on Earth--
比如鈾
like uranium ore--
它們的放射性來自於原子的裂變
comes from the disintegration of atoms.
但宇宙射線具有不同的性質
But cosmic rays were of a different nature.
它們的能量更強大
They were far more powerful
比當時赫斯的世界中任何一種已知物質都要強
than anything known in Hess's world.
科學家們探索了20年
Scientists wondered for two decades
想要知道是什麼東西產生了宇宙射線
what could possibly produce cosmic rays.
下面介紹弗裏茨•茲威基
Enter Fritz Zwicky,
一個你從沒聽說過的最聰明的人
the most brilliant man you've never heard of.
1933年 他和一個同事發現
In 1933, he and a colleague discovered
某些恆星會突然變得非常耀眼
that some stars flare up to become as bright
亮度就和它們所在的星系差不多並延續好幾周
as their entire galaxy for a few weeks,
然後又會黯淡下來
before fading out again.
弗裏茨•茲威基是世界上第一個
Fritz Zwicky was the first person
瞭解這個現象的人
to understand what just happened.
他正確的推測出
He correctly surmised that this is the way
這代表著一顆大質量恆星的死亡
a massive star dies-- it blows
爆炸將恆星的物質拋入太空
its guts out into space.
他把這種恆星的死亡稱為"超新星"
He called this kind of stellar death a "supernova"...
並推測這顆垂死的恆星將會坍縮
and predicted that the dying star would shrink
從100萬英里的直徑收縮為10英里
from about a million miles across to only ten.
恆星的殘骸密度如此之大
This corpse would be so dense
一粒米那麼大的物質
that a single grain of it would weigh as much
就會和埃及大金字塔一樣重
as the Great Pyramid in Egypt.
它將幾乎由
It would consist almost entirely
一種叫中子的亞原子粒子組成
of subatomic particles called neutrons,
所以他也將這種奇異的物體稱為"中子星"
so he named these bizarre objects "neutron stars."
自從茲威基預測這個現象存在後的35年
And 35 years after Zwicky predicted their existence,
天文學家開始找到它們
astronomers began to find them.
我們將它們稱為"脈衝星"
We call them "pulsars"
它們在快速自轉的同時會發射出有規律的脈衝電波信號
when they spin rapidly and emit regular pulses of radio energy.
超新星與中子星都能發出
Supernovas and neutron stars could account
大量的宇宙射線
for a wide range of cosmic rays,
但不是能量最強的那種
but not the most energetic ones.
現在的科學還不能很好解釋這種現象
Nothing yet known to science
不過沒事
can explain them, and we're fine with that.
這就是我愛科學的原因之一
It's one of the things I love about science,
我們從不假裝自己知道所有的答案
we don't have to pretend we have all the answers.
茲威基還認為
Zwicky also came up with the idea
星系的重力會讓它四周的空間結構發生彎曲
that the gravity of a galaxy warps the fabric
就像放大鏡一樣
of space around it, to act like a lens.
從而讓在它後面的其它星系的光線
This distorts and magnifies light
在穿過這個星系時發生扭曲並放大的效應
from any other galaxy lying directly behind it.
因此地球上的天文學家們在觀測 具有相同距離的遙遠星系時
So, astronomers on Earth would see multiple images
會看到有多重圖像出現
of that same distant galaxy,
就好像遊樂園的哈哈鏡效果
deformed, as in a funhouse mirror.
他做出這一預測40年後 人們才開始發現這一現象真實存在
40 years after this prediction, we started finding them, too.
茲威基在1930年代還有另一個發現
And Zwicky made yet another discovery back in the 1930s.
在觀測後發座星系團時
While studying the Coma Cluster of galaxies,
他注意到星團的移動方式很有意思
he noticed something funny about the way they moved.
它的移動速度很快
The galaxies were going way too fast,
在這麼快的速度下 這個星團早就該飛散了
so fast that they should've been flying apart from each other,
因為在所有這些星系中的恆星
because all the stars in all those galaxies
它們的引力太小 無法維繫整個星團的穩定
had far too little gravity to hold the cluster together.
茲威基認為
Zwicky thought
一定有某種力量將它們維繫在一起
that something else must be binding them to each other.
這看不見找不著的神秘部分
That mysterious missing component
它的重量至少是星團中所有的恆星總重的
would have to weigh something like 50 times as much
50倍以上
as the stars themselves.
但沒人對他的超前見解感興趣
But no one paid much attention to this wild notion.
認為那不過是茲威基的又一個瘋狂的想法
Just another one of Zwicky's crazy ideas.
在我們的太陽系
In our solar system,
位於內圈的行星水星 它的移動速度
the innermost planet, Mercury, moves much faster
要比最外圈的行星海王星快許多
than the outermost one, Neptune.
聽上去這很順理成章 對不
And that makes sense, right?
你越是用力推拉一個物體 它的速度也就越快
The harder you push or pull on something, the faster it goes.
太陽的引力隨距離的增加而會減弱
The Sun's gravity weakens with increasing distance,
因此 距離太陽更遠的行星移動得更慢
so, the planets that are farther from the Sun move more slowly.
人們認為星系最外層的恆星
Everyone expected that the outermost stars in a galaxy
也應該是這樣移動的
would act the same way.
大部分的恆星都向著星系的中心集中
Most of the stars are concentrated towards the center,
因此 它們的重力總和會牽引其它的恆星
so, their collective gravity pulls on the other stars
如同太陽牽引行星一樣
the same way the Sun pulls on the planets.
可是在1970年
But in the 1970s, when astronomer
天文學家維拉·魯賓在研究僊女座星系時
Vera Rubin studied the Andromeda Galaxy,
她發現這個星系的外層恆星並沒有遵循這個規律
she discovered that the outer stars obeyed no such rule.
它們與太陽系的外層行星不一樣
Unlike the outer planets of the solar system,
星系外層恆星的速度
the outer stars in the galaxy were all going at the same speed
與星系內層恆星的速度是一樣的
as the stars that were closer in,
它們移動得甚至比人們預想中的還要快
and they were moving way faster than expected.
"太有意思了" 維拉想道
"That's funny," Vera thought.
"僊女座星系里一定有古怪"
"There must be something weird about the Andromeda Galaxy."
於是 她又觀測另一個星系
So she looked at another galaxy.
發現了同樣的現象
Same story.
再下一個 也是如此
And another.
維拉一共觀測了60個星系
Vera studied 60 galaxies
發現所有的星系
and found that all of them
似乎都違背了萬有引力定律
seemed to be violating the Law of Gravity,
這是物理學中的核心理論
a core principle of physics.
一開始 她的同事們對這個現象表示質疑
After some initial healthy skepticism,
隨後他們開始動手自己觀測
her colleagues looked for themselves,
結果發現維拉的觀測結果是正確的
and found that Vera was right.
但並非是牛頓的萬有引力定律有問題
It's not that Isaac Newton had gotten the Law of Gravity wrong;
而是維拉·魯賓發現了
Vera Rubin had discovered that the gravity
某種巨大而又不可見的引力
of something massive and invisible
在迫使星星們移動加快
was forcing the stars to go fast.
然後 有人想起了瘋狂的老茲威基的說法
And then, someone remembered crazy old Fritz Zwicky,
那不明來源的引力
and the unknown source of gravity
肯定是存在於星系團中
in the galaxy clusters
1933年的時候 他就將其稱之為"暗物質"
that he called "dark matter," back in 1933.
維拉·魯賓證實了
Vera Rubin had verified the existence
一個全新的 更遼闊的宇宙的存在
of a new, much larger cosmos.
它與我們過去以為很瞭解的那個宇宙一樣
And just like the one we thought we knew,
充滿了奧秘
it was filled with mystery.
暗物質完全是探測不到的
Dark matter is completely unobservable,
但它會產生引力效應
except for its gravitational effect,
這會加速可見的恆星與星系的移動速度
which makes visible stars and galaxies move faster.
它的性質同樣是一個謎
Its nature is another deep mystery.
魯賓提供的證據表明 這個不可見的宇宙
Rubin had provided the evidence for an invisible universe
比我們已知的宇宙要大10倍以上
nearly ten times more massive than the one we thought we knew.
就好比暗夜裏站在海邊的人
It was as if we had been standing on the seashore
錯誤地認為
at night, mistakenly believing
海浪上的小泡沫 就是大海的全部
that the froth on the waves was all there was to the ocean.
維拉·魯賓觀測恆星時意識到了
Vera Rubin looked at the stars and realized
眼前的星星只不過是海浪上的小泡沫
they were merely the foam on the waves,
海洋最壯闊的部分 還不被人類知曉
and that the greatest part of the ocean remained unknown.
且慢
But wait.
這變得越來越瘋狂了
It gets crazier.
我們的銀河系
Our Milky Way Galaxy,
有數百億顆恆星
a few hundred billion stars,
還有無數的星雲與塵埃
plus the clouds of gas and dust,
那些東西過去曾是 未來也會再變為恆星
the stuff of once and future stars--
宇宙中還有上百億個其它星系--所有這些
and about a hundred billion other galaxies-- all of that,
再加上還沒統計進去的
including those uncounted billions of trillions
數以億兆計的行星 衛星和彗星
of planets, moons, and comets--
它們的總和還只不過是這個宇宙的百分之五
amounts to only five percent of what is actually there.
因為有個更大的未解之謎
Because there's a bigger unsolved mystery
比暗物質更神秘
than dark matter--
那就是暗能量
dark energy, which makes up even more of the cosmos
它佔據著大部分的宇宙並驅動著它的膨脹
and drives its expansion.
弗裏茨•茲威基發現的超新星
And it was Fritz Zwicky's supernovas
為人類揭示了一條顯示其存在的途徑
that lit the way to the revelation of its existence.
舉個例子 一顆恆星耗盡了它所有的核燃料後
In one scenario, a star consumes all of its nuclear fuel...
它先是冷卻下來
then cools,
然後在自身引力的作用下突然塌縮
and suddenly collapses under its own gravity.
隨後在聚變的反作用力下恆星會發生巨大的爆炸
The star rebounds in a massive explosion,
最後只遺留下一顆中子星或是一個黑洞
leaving behind a neutron star or a black hole.
由於爆發前那顆恆星的質量
Since the mass of the original star
上下浮動的區間很大
can fall within a wide range,
它變為超新星後的峰值亮度
its peak brightness as a supernova
也會有很大的不同
can also vary widely.
因此我們不能從亮度來判斷
So, you can't tell how far away it is
這顆星星離我們有多遠
just from how bright it looks.
一顆較近的超新星亮度看起來也許就會和在較遠地方
A relatively nearby supernova
爆發的超新星差不多 就算另一顆的爆發強度更大
might appear just as bright as one that was more powerful, but farther away.
但還有另外一種超新星
But there's another kind of supernova
它只有一種爆發強度
that comes in only one strength.
它看上去彷彿就是激烈的探戈舞終曲時
It marks the violent grand finale
一顆紅巨星與一顆紅矮星翩翩共舞的宏大場景
of a tango danced by a giant star and a dwarf.
當這兩顆星的運行軌道互相接近時
As the two stars orbit closely around each other,
紅巨星外層的氣體會傾瀉而出
the giant sheds its outer layers of gas
流到紅矮星上
onto the dwarf.
當紅矮星增加的重量
When the added weight becomes too much
超過了它所能承受的極限時
for it to bear,
星體就會像一顆巨大的核炸彈一樣爆炸
the dwarf detonates like a stupendous thermonuclear bomb.
有持續好幾周的時間
For a few weeks,
天空中這顆超新星的亮度
the brilliance of such a supernova rivals
會超過它的星系中其他恆星亮度的總和
the combined light of all the stars in its galaxy.
這種類型的超新星
This kind of supernova
它們輸出的最大能量值是相同的
always has the same maximum power output,
它大約比太陽亮50億倍
about five billion times brighter than our Sun.
通過巨大的天文望遠鏡
With big telescopes,
我們可以在非常遙遠的星系中看到它們
we can see them in galaxies very far away,
即使它就位於可觀測宇宙的邊緣
out toward the edge of the observable universe.
因為所有這種類型的超新星具有相同的亮度
Because all such supernovas have the same wattage,
因此 它們是用於測量距離的理想工具
they're ideal tools for measuring distances
適用於宇宙中哪怕是最遙遠的星系
to the farthest reaches of the universe.
我們也稱之為"標準燭光"
We call them "standard candles."
1929年 埃德溫•哈勃發現宇宙正在膨脹
In 1929, Edwin Hubble discovered that the universe is expanding.
遙遠的星系正在遠離彼此
The distant galaxies are drifting away from one another.
後來我們知道了
Later, we learned
宇宙的膨脹始於140億年前
that the expansion began some 14 billion years ago
從"宇宙大爆炸" 開始的那一刻起
with the explosive birth of the universe-- the big bang.
人們曾以為
Everybody assumed
宇宙的膨脹速度會慢下來
that the rate of expansion would be slowing down,
這是由於宇宙各部分之間的引力
due to the mutual pull of gravity
互相牽引的結果
between all the parts of the universe.
如果有足夠多的暗物質
If there is enough dark matter,
它的引力最終會將宇宙的膨脹停止下來
its gravity would eventually bring the expansion to a stop,
宇宙又會縮回到原點
and the universe would then fall back on itself.
照這樣推理 宇宙中的萬物終究會在
In that case, everything would eventually collapse
一次大擠壓中全面崩潰
in a big crunch.
但反過來說 如果宇宙中的暗物質再少一些
On the other hand, if the universe had less dark matter,
宇宙的膨脹就會永遠繼續下去
the expansion would continue forever,
只是速度會越來越慢
just getting slower and slower.
兩支互相競爭的天文學家團隊
Two competing teams of astronomers
同時在觀測著遙遠星系中的這些超新星
were observing those supernovas in distant galaxies.
這可以說是另一個
It turned out to be another one
"有意思"的時刻
of those "that's funny" moments.
1998年 這兩隻獨立的研究團隊
In 1998, both teams independently came
做出了同樣的結論
to the same conclusion.
宇宙的膨脹不僅沒有減緩
The expansion isn't slowing down at all...
而且還在不停的加速
it's speeding up.
這意味著宇宙會永遠膨脹下去
This means the universe will continue to expand forever.
宇宙中似乎有一股神秘的力量
There seems to be a mysterious force in the universe,
它的規模龐大得足以壓倒一切引力
one that overwhelms gravity on the grandest scale
將宇宙分開
to push the cosmos apart.
宇宙中大部分的能量
Most of the energy of the universe is bound up
都被這股看不見的力量束縛著
in this unknown force.
我們稱之為"暗能量"
We call it "dark energy,"
可這個名字就和"暗物質"一樣
but that name, like "dark matter,"
我們不知道它是什麼 只能強給它起個名字而已
is merely a code word for our ignorance.
我們承認不知道所有問題的答案
It's okay not to know all the answers.
承認自己的無知
It's better to admit our ignorance
總比強行認可那些可能錯誤的答案好
than to believe answers that might be wrong.
假裝自己什麼都懂 就是關上了
Pretending to know everything closes the door
通往真相的大門
to finding out what's really there.
今晚 我們的飛船航行到了
Tonight, our ships sail
更奇異的水域
into even more exotic waters.
跟我來
Come with me.
人類只有兩艘飛船冒險進入了
Only two of our ships have ventured
星際空間中的黑暗大洋
into the great dark ocean of interstellar space.
這是史上最長的冒險之旅
The longest odyssey in all of history
它開始於1977年
was launched back in 1977--
美國宇航局的旅行者1號與旅行者2號
NASA's Voyager 1 and 2.
這兩艘飛船以每小時4萬英里的速度行進
The Voyagers move about 40,000 miles an hour.
它們讓人類得以第一次近距離觀察
They gave us our first close-up look
木星上的大紅斑
at Jupiter's Great Red Spot,
那是比地球的尺寸還要大三倍的颶風
a hurricane three times the size of Earth
其中一個颶風至少在1644年就已經開始刮起
and one that's been raging since at least 1644,
並第一次被人類觀測到
when it was first observed.
所以我們知道 這些颶風至少可以延續數千年
For all we know, it could be thousands of years old.
旅行者號還發現了 在木星的衛星
The Voyagers discovered the first active volcano
木衛一上有活火山的存在
on another world, on Jupiter's moon Io...
在木衛二的冰層下
and an ocean beneath the icy surface
則存在著海洋
of the moon Europa...
它可能擁有比地球至少多2倍的液態水
with at least twice as much water as we have here on Earth.
旅行者號還勇敢的飛越了土星環
The Voyagers dared to fly across Saturn's rings
發現它是由數以百計的圓環帶組成
and revealed that they were made of hundreds of thin bands
而這些圓環帶則是由小雪球組成
of orbiting snowballs.
在土星的巨大衛星土衛六上
On Saturn's giant moon Titan,
旅行者號發現了比地球濃厚4倍的大氣層
Voyager detected an atmosphere four times denser than Earth's.
暗示著在土衛六上有可能存在甲烷的海洋
That hinted at the existence of hydrocarbon seas on Titan,
這一點後來被證實了
which we later confirmed.
旅行者2號讓人類第一次得到了
Voyager 2 gave us our first portrait
最外層的行星 海王星的肖像
of the outermost planet, Neptune...
海王星上狂風咆哮 風速達每小時1000英里
where the winds roar at 1,000 miles per hour...
在它的衛星海衛一上
and its moon Triton, where geysers
間歇泉能把沸騰的液氮噴到5英里高
of boiling nitrogen shoot five miles high.
旅行者號成功的完成了
Voyager successfully completed its mission of discovery
它對外層行星的觀測任務
to the outer planets,
但它進入黑暗世界的冒險之旅
but its odyssey into the darkness
才剛剛開始
was just beginning.
在發射後的35年
35 years after its launch,
旅行者1號成為人類第一個
Voyager 1 became the first of our spacecraft
進入未知領域的太空飛船
to enter an uncharted realm.
太陽向各個方向不斷地發射出
The Sun is constantly shooting out streams
帶電的粒子流
of charged particles in all directions,
粒子流的時速達100萬英里
moving at a million miles an hour.
這就是太陽風 它擴散後的區域是一個巨大的磁泡
This solar wind blows a vast magnetic bubble,
形成了太陽風層 它一直延伸到最外層的行星之外
our heliosphere, that extends beyond the outer planets.
它把從星際空間進入的稀薄氣體向外推
It pushes out against the thin gas of interstellar space.
這就是一個世界的盡頭 另一個世界的起點
There's a border where one ends and the other begins.
旅行者1號向地球報告說
Voyager 1 reported back to Earth
它的探測器正在遭遇
that its detectors were being pummeled
越來越多的宇宙射線攻擊
by more and more cosmic rays.
直至現在 我們還是不知道
Until then, we didn't know
哪裏才是浩瀚星際大洋的開始
where the interstellar ocean began.
旅行者1號不斷前行
Voyager 1 pressed on
它穿越了人類從未穿越的邊界
past a boundary we had never crossed before.
太陽風層為我們阻擋了大部分致命的宇宙射線
The heliosphere shields us from most of the deadly cosmic rays.
當太陽風如驟雨般爆發時
When stormy solar winds blow,
太陽風層也會隨之擴張
this zone of protection grows;
太陽風平靜時 它會縮小
in calm solar weather, it shrinks.
當銀河系附近出現超新星爆發時
When a star goes supernova in our galactic neighborhood...
爆發後的星體殘骸
the debris from the exploded star
會將太陽風層推向太陽的方向
pushes the heliosphere back towards the Sun.
如果殘骸的能量足夠大
If it's strong enough to push it
它就有可能會進入地球的軌道
all the way back to Earth's orbit,
我們的星球就會沐浴在具有輻射性的超新星殘骸中
our planet gets a radioactive bath of supernova debris.
好在這樣的情況不常發生
Luckily, this doesn't happen very often.
最後一次出現是在200萬年前
The last one was perhaps two million years ago.
鄰近的一顆恆星爆發了
A neighboring star explodes a million years
地球上還要再過100萬年才會出現人類這個物種
before there's even such a thing as the human species.
我們從何得知此事
How can we possibly know this?
因為死亡的恆星會留下蹤跡
Because the dying star left its traces
它就藏在海洋下幾英里處
miles below the surface of the ocean.
這是錳結核 就像這塊小石頭
Manganese nodules, small rocks like this one,
它分散在深海的海床上
are scattered over much of the deep sea floor.
它的生長速度非常緩慢
They grow very slowly.
100萬年才能長1毫米
I'm talking a millimeter in a million years,
一層層的堆疊生長
layer upon layer.
錳結核與細菌共生
These nodules grow in partnership with bacteria
它們吸取溶解在海水中的礦物質
by taking up minerals dissolved in the seawater.
超新星會產生一種具有放射性的鐵
A supernova produces a radioactive form of iron,
它和地球上自然產生的任何一種物質都不一樣
unlike anything made by natural processes on Earth.
研究人員發現了這種鐵的痕跡
Researchers found telltale traces of this iron
它就長在錳結核中
in a thin layer below the surface
外殼下的一個淺層裏
of the manganese nodules.
研究人員把已知的錳結核的生長速率
They used the known rate of growth of the nodules
和每層的生長時間聯繫起來
to date that layer and to connect it
就能知道億萬年前恆星滅亡的命運了
to the fate of a star that perished eons ago.
你看到的是石頭
The difference between seeing nothing but a pebble
但在科學家眼裏 這是深藏在裏面的宇宙的歷史
and reading the history of the cosmos inscribed inside it
這就是科學的力量
is science.
星際大洋黑暗而深遠
The interstellar ocean is dark and deep.
從那裏看 太陽只不過是天空中一顆最亮的恆星
Out here, the Sun is just the brightest star in the sky.
旅行者號依然保持著
Yet the Voyagers maintain their regular communications
與美國宇航局噴氣推進實驗室定期的聯繫
with NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
他們的交流要經過1光時
talking back and forth across the light-hours
這就是太空船與母港之間的距離
that separate these ships from their home port.
再沒有人造的物體
No other objects touched by human hands
曾如此冒險遠離家園
have ever ventured this far from home.
當這些飛船
Even after they lose their ability
失去了與人類通訊的能力之後
to respond to our command,
旅行者號最後一個也是最長的一個任務
the last and, by far, the longest phase
就此拉開序幕
of the Voyager mission will begin.
1979年 當旅行者號繞著木星旋轉時
Back in 1979, when both Voyagers rounded Jupiter,
木星的巨大引力就像一個彈弓
its massive gravity acted as a slingshot,
把它們拋出太陽系
flinging them out of the solar system
讓它們得以在銀河系的恆星間航行
to travel among the stars of our galaxy
時間是10億年
for a billion years.
當年 卡爾•薩根意識到旅行者號的任務
Carl Sagan recognized that the Voyager mission
為人類提供了兩張接近永恆的機票
offered two free tickets to something approaching eternity.
他組建了一個小隊 創造了一些信息
He assembled a small team to create a message
以便在未來的某一天
to any civilization that might, one day,
當某個文明遇到這個廢棄的航天器時可以讀到它
encounter the derelict spacecraft.
26個世紀前
26 centuries ago,
亞述國王以撒哈頓寫道
the Assyrian king Esarhaddon wrote...
"朕以青銅鑄碑
"I had monuments made of bronze
銘文於泥版
and inscriptions of baked clay.
遺之於基石 傳之於後世"
I left them in the foundations for future times."
這些象形圖形延續了這一古老的傳統
These hieroglyphics continue that ancient tradition.
它們被刻印在蓋子上 上面的信息被設計成
They are inscribed on the cover of a message designed
方便其它世界或後世的生物閱讀
to be read by the beings of other worlds and times.
我們人類與外星文明之間
What could we possibly have in common
有可能會有什麼共同點呢
with an alien civilization
他們會有自己與眾不同的進化史
with its own separate evolutionary history
甚至有可能比我們更先進
and one so far advanced beyond us
能自由遨遊於星際空間
that they can patrol interstellar space?
但至少有一樣東西
One thing at least,
是宇宙間通用的語言
a universal language...
科學
science.
引力的束縛是很難被打破的
It's hard to break the bonds of gravity.
想要在宇宙之海中暢遊
You can only sail the cosmic seas
你必須通曉數學與物理
if you speak mathematics and physics.
氫是宇宙中最常見的元素
Hydrogen is the most common element in the universe.
氫原子中的電子
The electron in a hydrogen atom
在它的旋轉方向上作翻轉運動
flips the direction of its spin
它的速率或頻率是恆定的
at a constant rate, or frequency.
氫原子就像是個迷你的天然時鐘
Hydrogen atoms are like tiny natural clocks--
滴…答…走動
tick... tock.
這就意味著我們與外星人共同擁有
Now we have a unit of time in common
相同的一個時間單位
with the extraterrestrials.
瞭解了這個
This will come in handy when we get to the next level
再轉到下一個信息時就好理解了
of the message.
下面的信息是指示出我們在宇宙中的位置
Here's our return address in space.
脈衝星是快速旋轉的中子星
Pulsars are rapidly-spinning neutron stars
它們會發出定期爆發的無線電波
that give off regular bursts of radio waves.
你可以根據這個來設定時間
You can set your clock by them.
太陽位於這個示意圖的中心
The Sun is at the center of this diagram,
這些線條指向14顆最近的脈衝星
and the lines point to the 14 nearest pulsars.
有一個簡單的標籤指示出了每顆脈衝星的特有頻率
A simple code labels each pulsar with its unique frequency,
並用氫原子
using the ticktock of the hydrogen atom
作為計時單位
as the unit of time.
因此 外星的天文學家能利用這張示意圖
So alien astronomers could use this diagram
來定位出旅行者號航天器的母星
to locate the home star of the Voyager spacecraft
在我們銀河系中的位置
in our galaxy.
他們還能知道
They could also tell
這艘航天器已經發射多久了
how long ago the spacecraft was launched.
這一點很重要
And that's important because the Voyager record
因為旅行者號的外殼設計壽命是10億年
has a projected shelf life of 1,000 million years.
就想像一下你是一個
Become an extraterrestrial archaeologist
外星球的考古學家
for a few moments.
有一架人造航天器完成了它在星際大洋中的使命
An artifact has been fished out of the interstellar ocean.
它是由外星智慧生命
It was made by beings
在10億年前建造的
that lived about a billion years ago.
你要怎樣通過它瞭解他們和他們的世界
What would you make of them and their world?
他們給我們送來了他們的音樂
They've sent us their music
還有用59種人類語言說出的問候方式
and greetings in 59 human languages.
這是地球上一位小孩子向你打招呼
Hello from the children of planet Earth.
鯨魚的語言
And one whale language.
還有一串聲音的組合 包括土星五號火箭發射的聲音
And a sound essay that includes a Saturn V rocket launch.
一位母親對她新生的嬰兒說的話
A mother's first words to her newborn baby.
哦 來吧
Oh, come on now.
做個好孩子…做個好孩子
Be a good boy... be a good boy.
一位剛剛墜入愛河的年輕女子的腦波
The brain waves of a young woman newly fallen in love.
還有脈衝星的聲音
And the sound of a pulsar.
所有這些都能存在10億年之久
All of that will live for a billion years.
10億年有多久
How long is a billion years?
如果你能把創世大爆炸以來的時間
If you compress all the time since the Big Bang,
也就是宇宙誕生的那一刻開始的時間
the explosive birth of the universe,
壓縮成一個地球年的話
into a single Earth year,
10億年就相當於這1年中的1個月
a billion years is about one month of that year.
10億年前的地球上發生了些什麼
What was happening on Earth a billion years ago?
大部分的地球陸地都聚集在一個超大陸上
Most of Earth's land was amassed into a supercontinent
我們稱之為羅迪尼亞大陸
called Rodinia.
這是一個荒地 沒有動物 沒有植物
It was a barren desert-- no animals, no plants.
10億年前
A billion years ago, there wasn't enough oxygen
空氣裏沒有足夠的氧以形成臭氧層
in our atmosphere to form an ozone layer,
沒有它的保護
and without it, ultraviolet radiation
紫外線會阻止生命在陸地上生存
prevented life from colonizing the land.
羅迪尼亞大陸看上去可能更像火星
Rodinia probably looked more like Mars
而不像今天的地球
than present-day Earth.
巨大的海洋世界產生大暴雨
The giant world ocean produced huge rainstorms
造成洪水和侵蝕
causing flooding and erosion.
冰川形成 它們緩慢而無情的運動著
Glaciers formed, and their slow but relentless movements
把陸地塑造成新的樣子
carved the land into new shapes.
單細胞的生物主宰著海洋
Single-celled organisms dominated the oceans,
被稱為"微生物席"的生物集群地已經開始出現
but some existed in colonies called "microbial mats,"
第一個多細胞生物很快會演變形成
and the first multicellular organisms would soon evolve.
10億年後
And a billion years from now,
今天的地球又會變成怎樣…
what will Earth be like...
我們的城市 埃及的金字塔
long after our cities, the Egyptian pyramids,
洛基山脈 是否早已被侵蝕為塵土
the Rocky Mountains have all been eroded to dust?
對於這麼久遠的時間來說
There are few things we can say with confidence
我們沒有幾件事是可以說得清的
about such a far distant time.
我們唯一可以肯定的是
The only thing we can say for sure
我們所認識的地球會發生巨變
is that Earth as we know it will be so changed
幾乎沒有人會認得出 這曾經是我們的家園
that we would scarcely recognize it as home.
但就算是10億年後
But even a thousand million years from now,
我們人類的本性
something of who we were and the music that we made
和我們在久遠的春天寫下的音樂
in that long-ago spring...
都會延續下去
will live on.
在如此遙遠的未來 我們的太陽系
In that distant future, our Sun will have completed
完成了繞著銀河系中心公轉4圈的歷程
another four orbits around the center of the galaxy...
旅行者號早已飛到了遠離太陽的領域
...and the Voyagers will have ventured far from the Sun.
卡爾•薩根曾是旅行者號影像小組的一員
Carl Sagan was a member of Voyager's imaging team,
旅行者號拍攝的最後一張照片來自於他的想法
and it was his idea that Voyager take one last picture.
在一代人以前
A generation before,
阿波羅登月飛行的最後一位宇航員
an astronaut on the last Apollo flight to the Moon
照下了一張地球的全景照片
had taken a picture of the whole Earth--
這是一個沒有邊界的行星
the planet as a world without borders.
它成了一種新意識的象徵
It became an icon of a new consciousness.
卡爾實現了這個過程的下一步
Carl realized the next step in this process.
他說服了美國宇航局把旅行者一號的鏡頭
He convinced NASA to turn the Voyager 1 camera
在飛過海王星時 轉回地球
back towards Earth when the spacecraft went beyond Neptune
讓它最後看一眼家園 他所說的那個
for one last look homeward at what he called...
泛著蒼白藍光的小點
the pale blue dot.
在那裏
That's here.
那是家園
That's home.
那是我們
That's us.
在那裏 你愛的每個人
On it, everyone you love,
你認識的每個人
everyone you know,
你聽說過的每個人
everyone you ever heard of,
在這世上存在過的每個人
every human being who ever was,
度過了自己的一生
lived out their lives.
聚集在這裏的 是我們的歡樂和痛苦
The aggregate of our joy and suffering,
是成千上萬的宗教信仰 意識形態
thousands of confident religions, ideologies,
和經濟學說
and economic doctrines,
每個獵手與覓食者
every hunter and forager,
每個英雄與懦夫
every hero and coward,
每個文明的創立者和毀滅者
every creator and destroyer of civilization,
每個國王與農夫
every king and peasant,
每對年輕的愛侶
every young couple in love,
每一個母親與父親 充滿希望的孩子們
every mother and father, hopeful child,
發明家與探險家
inventor and explorer,
每一位高尚的教師 每一位貪腐的政客
every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician,
每一位超級明星 每一位最高領袖
every superstar, every supreme leader,
人類史上的每一位聖人和罪人
every saint and sinner in the history of our species,
都生活在這裏
lived there...
如一粒微塵
on a mote of dust
懸浮在一束陽光之中
suspended... in a sunbeam.
地球是在浩瀚的宇宙背景下的
The Earth is a very small stage
一個很小的舞台
in a vast, cosmic arena.
想想過去的血流成河
Think of the rivers of blood
那為帝王將相而流的血
spilled by all those generals and emperors
只為讓他們在光榮和勝利中
so that in glory and triumph
成為瞬間的偉人
they could become the momentary masters
佔有那一個小點中…那一小部分
of a fraction... of a dot.
想想那無盡的殘酷
Think of the endless cruelties visited
圖像裏那一個像素點的某個角落的民眾
by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel
每天把這殘酷施加到與他們沒什麼區別的
on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants
另一個角落的民眾身上
of some other corner.
他們為何常常誤解
How frequent their misunderstandings,
他們為何渴望殺死對方
how eager they are to kill one another,
他們的憎恨為何如此狂熱
how fervent their hatreds.
我們在裝模做樣
Our posturings,
我們自以為很重要
our imagined self-importance,
妄想著我們人類地位特殊
the delusion that we have some privileged position
在宇宙中與眾不同
in the universe,
這一切 都因這泛著蒼白藍光的小點而動搖
are challenged by this point of pale light.
我們的星球
Our planet...
不過是一粒孤獨的微塵
is a lonely speck in the great,
籠罩在偉大的宇宙黑暗之中
enveloping cosmic dark.
我們默默無聞
In our obscurity,
沉浸在無盡的浩瀚裏
in all this vastness,
沒有一絲線索顯示 除了我們自己
there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere
還有誰能拯救我們
to save us from ourselves.
地球是目前已知唯一有生命的世界
The Earth is the only world known so far to harbor life.
生命再無其他去處
There is nowhere else,
至少在不久的將來 亦是如此
at least in the near future,
沒有外星球 供人類遷移
to which our species could migrate.
只可參觀
Visit, yes.
不能定居
Settle, not yet.
不管你喜歡與否
Like it or not,
現在 只有地球供我們立足
for the moment, the Earth is where we make our stand.
據說研習天文 可以讓人謙卑
It has been said that astronomy is a humbling
塑造人心 磨煉個性
and character-building experience.
也許再沒有更好的方法
There is perhaps no better demonstration
能比這遙遠的畫面
of the folly of human conceits
更好地顯示出人類的自負與愚蠢
than this distant image.
對我而言 它強調了我們的責任
To me, it underscores our responsibility
要對人更友善
to deal more kindly with one another
懂得珍惜與愛護
and to preserve and cherish
這泛著蒼白藍光的小點
the pale blue dot,
是我們知道的唯一的家園
the only home we've ever known.
我們是如何
How did we,
在這一粒微塵上居住的渺小生物
tiny creatures living on that speck of dust,
是如何千方百計地把宇宙飛船
ever manage to figure out how to send spacecraft
送入銀河的星星之間
out among the stars of the Milky Way?
就在幾百年前 也就是宇宙歷中的幾秒時間
Only a few centuries ago, a mere second of cosmic time,
我們尚不知道自己身在何方 時為何時
we knew nothing of where or when we were.
對宇宙的其他部分一無所知
Oblivious to the rest of the cosmos,
我們身居囚籠
we inhabited a kind of prison--
活在自己的小宇宙裏
a tiny universe
困在堅殼之中
bounded by a nutshell.
我們是如何逃出囚籠
How did we escape from the prison?
是因為世世代代探索者的不懈努力
It was the work of generations of searchers
他們發自內心地遵從5條簡單規則
who took five simple rules to heart.
質疑權威
Question authority.
不輕信人言
No idea is true just because someone says so,
包括自己在內
including me.
獨立思考
Think for yourself.
自我質疑
Question yourself.
不因自己想要相信 而相信任何事情
Don't believe anything just because you want to.
相信不代表能成為現實
Believing something doesn't make it so.
依靠觀察與實驗
Test ideas by the evidence gained
以實證檢驗想法
from observation and experiment.
如果自己喜歡的想法沒有通過全面的檢驗
If a favorite idea fails a well-designed test,
它就是錯的
it's wrong!
樂觀一點
Get over it.
遵循證據 無論它指向哪裏
Follow the evidence, wherever it leads.
如果沒有證據 不妄下定論
If you have no evidence, reserve judgment.
也許最重要的規則就是
And perhaps the most important rule of all...
要記住 你也會犯錯
Remember, you could be wrong.
即使是最優秀的科學家
Even the best scientists
也曾經在某些事情上犯錯
have been wrong about some things.
牛頓 愛因斯坦
Newton, Einstein,
還有歷史上每一位偉大的科學家
and every other great scientist in history,
他們都犯過錯
they all made mistakes.
這很正常 是人都會犯錯
Of course they did-- they were human.
科學讓我們不再欺騙自己
Science is a way to keep from fooling ourselves...
欺騙別人
and each other.
科學家們有罪嗎
Have scientists known sin?
有的
Of course.
我們曾濫用科學
We have misused science, just as we have
就像手邊的工具一樣隨意使用
every other tool at our disposal,
因此我們不能把科學
and that's why we can't afford
放在少數的掌權者手中
to leave it in the hands of a powerful few.
當科學更多的屬於全人類時
The more science belongs to all of us,
它就越不會被亂用
the less likely it is to be misused.
科學的價值能阻止
These values undermine the appeals
狂熱與無知
of fanaticism and ignorance
畢竟
and, after all,
宇宙的大部分是黑暗的
the universe is mostly dark,
只有點點的星光點綴著
dotted by islands of light.
瞭解了地球的年齡 恆星的距離
Learning the age of the Earth or the distance to the stars
生命的演變
or how life evolves--
這會讓世界有什麼區別
what difference does that make?
嗯 這取決於
Well, part of it depends on how big a universe
你願意生活在多大的宇宙裏
you're willing to live in.
有些人喜歡小宇宙
Some of us like it small.
沒關係
That's fine.
完全可以理解
Understandable.
但我喜歡大的宇宙
But I like it big.
當我把這一切放在我的心裏 我的腦海裏
And when I take all of this into my heart and my mind,
我會感到心情振奮
I'm uplifted by it.
當這種感覺涌起 我希望看到它是真實的
And when I have that feeling, I want to know that it's real,
而不僅僅是我腦海中的想像
that it's not just something happening inside my own head,
因為這就是真相
because it matters what's true,
而我們的想像
and our imagination is nothing
與自然中令人驚嘆的現實相比 根本不算什麼
compared with Nature's awesome reality.
我想要知道 在那黑暗的地方有什麼
I want to know what's in those dark places,
在創世大爆炸之前發生了什麼
and what happened before the Big Bang.
我想要知道 在宇宙的視界之外是什麼
I want to know what lies beyond the cosmic horizon,
生命又是如何起源的
and how life began.
宇宙中有沒有個地方
Are there other places in the cosmos
物質和能量在那裏被賦予
where matter and energy have become alive...
生命和意識
and aware?
我想要瞭解我們的先祖
I want to know my ancestors--
瞭解他們每一個人
all of them.
我想要成為一個美好而強大的聯接
I want to be a good, strong link
聯繫世世代代的人類
in the chain of generations.
我想要保護我的孩子們
I want to protect my children
以及未來的子孫後代
and the children of ages to come.
我們 代表著宇宙在這個世界的耳目
We, who embody the local eyes and ears
代表著宇宙在這個世界的想法與情感
and thoughts and feelings of the cosmos,
我們開始瞭解人類的起源
we've begun to learn the story of our origins--
思考繁星的故事 物質的演化
star stuff contemplating the evolution of matter,
追溯意識起源之前那條漫長的道路
tracing that long path by which it arrived at consciousness.
我們與這個星球上的其他生物
We and the other living things on this planet
攜帶著宇宙進化的遺產
carry a legacy of cosmic evolution
逾越了數十億年
spanning billions of years.
如果我們將這些知識銘記於心
If we take that knowledge to heart,
如果我們瞭解並熱愛大自然的本質
if we come to know and love nature as it really is,
我們的子孫們一定會記住我們
then we will surely be remembered by our descendants
因為我們是生命之鏈中美好而強大的一環
as good, strong links in the chain of life.
我們的子孫們也會繼續這神聖的探索
And our children will continue this sacred searching,
薪火相傳 不斷開拓
seeing for us as we have seen for those who came before,
就在這宇宙之中 發現我們做夢
discovering wonders yet undreamt of...
都想不到的奇跡
in the cosmos.
■
在製作這部紀錄片的字幕的過程中
越來越發現人類的渺小至極
世界永遠超出我們所想像的
總括而言 智慧 勇氣 倔強 都是科研人員必須擁有的特質
而這部紀錄片最後的那一段
也向大家作出了在科學世界探索的五大要素
這部紀錄片比你們書本上學到的東西還要多
儘管今天我們無法發掘到宇宙的全部奧妙
希望這部紀錄片能夠激發你
相信某一天 坐在螢幕前的你 特別是還年輕的你們
在未來將會能夠為我們解開謎團 為人類發展揭開全新的一頁
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal 個人總結 timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息